Apo.
なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜アポ＞
A pug that Hibito keeps as a pet in Houston.
ひびと
＜日々人がヒューストンで
飼っているパグ＞
His name comes from "Apollo," the mission to the moon.
＜名前の由来は かつて月へ行った
宇宙船のアポロ＞
But change one letter, and it's "Aho," which means idiot in Japanese.
＜でも 一文字違ったらアホに
なってしまう可哀想なやつ＞
He has a heart-shaped patch on his left side.
＜チャームポイントは 左肩にある
ハートマーク型の模様＞
He likes to eat hot dogs.
＜好きな食べ物はホットドッグ＞
＜特技は たぶん➡
He's especially good at playing with Serika.
せりかさんと たわむれること＞
He can serve as an accurate and brutally effective alarm clock.
ようしゃ
＜かなり正確 かつ容赦ない
目覚まし機能つき＞
ワンッ！ワンッ！ワンッ！
(南波日々人)ん～｡
(アポ)ワンッ！ワンッ！ワンッ！
ワンッ！ワンッ！ワンッ！
＜先日 私を一時的に全米の
ヒーローへと導いたのは➡
Not too long ago, Apo helped make me a hero...
このアポだったりも
したのだが…＞
＜よりによって日々人の打ち上げ
直前に いなくなるなんて！＞
But now he's gone missing, right before Hibito's supposed to launch.
本当は 自由になりたいんだろ？
ベイベー！
I know you want to be free, baby.
＜勝手にいなくなるような
アポではないと思うのだが…＞
I wouldn't have expected Apo to run off.
さあ走れ！そこには
自由が待っているんだぜ！➡
Now, go!
Your freedom awaits!
Go, go, go!
ゴー！ゴー！ゴー‼
ワンッ！ワンッ！
アポ～っ！
Apo!
Seven Days
Space Brothers
Before my uneasiness
was the end
of my happiness
I came to you
and we were one
Hello Hello
Let's fly
Here in this world we dream
and keep on dancing
Here among light and shadow
we keep changing
so that the wind doesn't let up
Even though the future is vague and unreliable
we are
not alone
#30 Dog, Old Man, and Alexander
(ﾊﾞｯｸｱｯﾌﾟｸﾙｰ)行ってらっしゃい｡
Good luck.
Bon voyage.
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)よい旅を！
Yeah.
Good luck.
行ってらっしゃい｡
おっ！行ってらっしゃ～い！
ヒビト！
Good luck, Hibito!
行って…くる！
I'm going up!
雲は散り始めているが
今の状態ではまだゴーは出せない｡
The skies are clearing, but we still can't give the go sign.
とりあえず 打ち上げの手順通り
作業を進めてくれ｡➡
Continue with the pre-launch process.
予定時刻の空を見て判断する｡
We'll see how it looks at launch before making a final decision.
３ヵ月後には
アズマ達のクルーも月へ向かう｡➡
In three months, Azuma's crew will set off for the moon.
それまで
６人でがんばってくれよ！
Until then, you six are on your own.
ＯＫ！
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)見てくれ ヒビト！
Okay.
Look, Hibito!
Tea Stem
ムッタに教わった
ラッキーな日本語だ！
Mutta taught me this lucky Japanese word.
Here's hoping the launch goes well.
この打ち上げが
うまくいくように｡
なるほど ラッキーだね｡
Yeah, lucky...
後ろもあるよ ほらっ！
君に幸あれ ヒビト！
I have another one on the back.
Half Off
Look!
God bless you, Hibito.
おまえもな ローリー｡
You, too, Lowry.
アポー！どこ行った～！
Apo! Where did you go?
みんな！アポを見なかった？
Hey, have you guys seen Apo?
Huh?
We tied him to a pole, but he ran off somehow...
つないでたのに
いなくなっちゃたんだよ！
Mu's off looking for him.
今 ムッ君が
捜し回ってるんだけど｡
Huh?
Oh, no... What should we do, dear?!
どうしよう お父さん！
どうしよう お父さん‼
Calm down. He must be somewhere.
落ち着け｡どっかには いる｡
(新田)そりゃな｡
No kidding.
これはあくまで僕の推理だけど…｡
This is just a guess,
日々人君の元に
向かってたりしてね｡➡
but he might be looking for Hibito.
つまり 発射台に｡➡
So he'd be heading for the launchpad.
だとしたら 泣けるねぇ～｡
That would be touching...
Um, wouldn't that be really dangerous?
あの…もしそうなら
相当 危ないんじゃ？
The launch creates a shock wave.
打ち上げの時の爆風とか…｡
⦅ギャフ！⦆
It will be fine.
つるみ
大丈夫ですよ｡危険区域には➡
There's a fence to keep animals out of the danger zone.
動物侵入防止のフェンスが張って
あります｡鳥なら入れますが…｡
Although birds still get in.
Because birds can fly, right?
なすだ
鳥なんか とりおさえろ ねえ｡➡
But that's why there have been instances when bald eagles got in, and launches were canceled.
まあでも だからね たまにあの～
なんですか あのあれですよ➡
ハクトウワシとか入っちゃって
打ち上げ中止とかになるんだよね｡
いや～ そんなことより
一番 心配なのはね～➡
But honestly, you should be more worried about...
ワニだよ ワニ｡
crocodiles.
み みんなで捜しましょう！
は はい！
L-Let's all look together.
R-Right!
≪パグ？見てないねぇ≫
A pug? I haven't seen one.
Oh, okay... Thanks.
あ～ そ～すか｡どうも｡
《誰か見てね～のかよ！》
No one's seen him?
やっべえなぁ～｡
This is bad...
こういうとこに入ってったら
もう見つけようがないぞ｡
If he ran in there, I'll never find him.
ホットドッグ！クソもらったぜ！
I got a shitty hot dog!
Stop cussing! Give that back!
(ティム)クソって言うな！返せ！
早く出て来いアポ～｡
日々人がいっちまうぞ｡
Show yourself, Apo...
Hibito's about to leave!
(グッ ギュッ)
(シュッ パチッ)
(プシュー カチッ)
≪カチャ≫
(ガシャン ガチャリ)
いやぁ すごい人ね あなた！
Wow, there are so many people, dear.
Yeah, only forty minutes left before launch.
ああ 打ち上げまで あと４０分か｡
今頃ヒビトは あの中ね｡
So Hibito's inside that thing?
天気は大丈夫かしら？
あれ？
Is the weather going to cooperate?
Huh?
(オバー)何？
アポそっくりのパグがいた｡
What is it?
I just saw a pug that looked exactly like Apo.
Maybe Mutta and his family are here.
ムッタ達じゃないの？
いや～ 全然 知らないじいさんが
連れてたから 違う犬だろ｡
No...
A strange old man was walking him, so it couldn't be Apo.
《晴れてきたな》
It's cleared up...
Makabe Kenji
おっ！ああ ケンジ｡
Oh, Kenji...
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ケンジ)もしもし ムッ君｡
アポ見つかった？
Hello? Mu?
Did you find Apo?
No, I haven't found him yet.
いや まだ見つかってない｡
I see...
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ケンジ)そっか…打ち上げが
決定したみたいだよ｡
They've confirmed they're launching.
Seriously?
マジで!?ん？
いた～！アポだ！
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ケンジ)えっ!?
There! It's Apo!
Huh?
あとで かけ直すよ！
I'll call you back!
あ ちょっと～ 待って～！
お～いっ！
Wait! Hold on!
Hey!
Oh?
おう！久しぶりだな
アレクサンダー！
It's been ages, Alexander.
乗ってくか？お？
Want a ride?
アレクサンダー？
Alexander?
あっ ムッ君！
うん あっ ホントに‼➡
Oh, Mu?
Really?!
アポ見つかったって｡
He found Apo.
よかった～｡
ホッ｡ホーッよ ホント！
一件落着｡
That's a relief...
Absolutely.
Case closed.
So, Mu, where are you now?
それでムッ君 今どこ？
ああ それが…
車ん中なんだけど➡
Uh, well...
I'm riding in a car,
どこに向かってんのか
俺にも わかんね～んだよ｡
but I have no idea where we're heading.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ケンジ)え!?
まあ 心配はいらね～よ｡
Huh?
Yeah, don't worry.
宇宙センターの中だし｡
みんなで打ち上げ見といて｡
We're still at the space center.
You guys, go watch the launch.
I'll be watching from somewhere.
俺もどっかで見てるから｡
《たぶん…》
I think...
うん…じゃあ また後で｡
See you later, then.
(ケンジ)大丈夫かな？
Will he be okay?
(ｽﾋﾟｰｶｰ:ｱﾅｳﾝｽ)打ち上げ２５分前｡
T minus 25 minutes.
どわっ！
おっとっと！
うぐっ！
Th-This old man is a rough driver!
《このじ～さん 運転荒れえ～！》
Doesn't NASA enforce the speed limit?
ナサ
《ＮＡＳＡには
スピード違反とかないの!?》
So you're from Japan?
あんた日本人だったのか！➡
I thought you were this Greek guy I used to know.
てっきり 知り合いのギリシア人
かと思って乗せちまったわ！
ニコラスもその頭しとるからな｡
You look a lot like Nikolas...
《ニコラス？さっきはｱﾚｸｻﾝﾀﾞｰって
言ってなかったか？》
Nikolas?
Didn't he call me Alexander?
《怪しいぞ～｡
何もんだ このじ～さん》
Something's fishy here.
Who is this old man?
言っとくが ワシがさらったんじゃ
ね～ぞ そのワンコ｡➡
Just so we're clear, I didn't snatch your dog.
そいつが ワシの
ホットドッグにつられて➡
He kept following my hot dogs.
ずっと ついて来やがったんだ｡➡
He must really love them.
よっぽど好きらしいな～
そのホットドッグが｡
《そこは…納得》
Yeah, that's plausible.
Uh, since we've established that I'm not an old acquaintance, could you drop us off?
あの 人違いってわかったんだから
もう降ろしてもらえないすか？
Why bother?
いいじゃねぇ～か｡
旅は道連れってヤツだ｡➡
Trips are more fun with a partner.
あんたもキャンディなめるか？
ワシの大好物だ｡
Want some candy?
I love these.
N-No thank you.
あ…いえ｡
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)あ～そうか｡ハハハハ！
Up to you.
Hmm?
このキャンディは 最初の
３０秒しか うまくないんでな｡➡
This candy is only good for thirty seconds.
ウッハハハハ！
《この じ～さんは
信用ならねぇ…》
I can't trust this guy.
《腕時計が…
ロラックスの時点で》
Not when he's wearing
a Rolax watch.
あ…あのさ どこへ行くかだけでも
教えてよ じ～さん｡
Say, can you tell me where we're going?
いいとこだよ いいとこ｡
そう心配すんな｡➡
A good place, a very good place.
Don't worry.
こう見えてもＮＡＳＡの職員だ｡
I'm a NASA employee.
《本当かよ…!?》
Really?
マサ
《ＭＡＳＡとかじゃね～のかよ》
Maybe he means MASA?
デニール･ヤング…｡
Deneil Young...
We're here.
着いたぞ 降りろ｡
Hop out.
What is this place?!
何だよ ここは…!?
な…ここ どこ!?
Wh-Where are we?
｢いいとこ｣ったろ｡➡
Isn't this a great place?
ほれ｡シャトル時代初期の
訓練施設だ｡➡
Look...
That's a training facility from the shuttle era.
もう２０年以上 使ってない｡
It hasn't be used in over twenty years.
こっちは もっと古いぞ｡➡
This one's even older.
昔のロケットの発射管制棟だ｡
It's an old blockhouse.
This is a blockhouse?
これが 管制棟…｡
こっち来い アレクサンダー｡
This way, Alexander.
That isn't my name.
だから 違うって！俺はムッタだ｡
I'm Mutta.
今日の打ち上げクルー
ナンバ･ヒビトのお兄ちゃんだ｡
My little brother, Nanba Hibito, is going into space today.
What? Really?
何!?そうだったか！ウハハハ‼➡
こりゃ失敬｡ムッタね｡ぷっ！
Excuse me.
Mutta, is it?
ワシの名はデニール･ヤング！
My name is Deneil Young!
Yeah, I saw.
いや さっき見たよ それ…｡
そうか ムッタっていうのか｡➡
Okay, so your name is Mutta.
助かるぜ｡アレクサンダーは
長いな～と思ってた｡
That helps.
Alexander was too long.
《知らね～よ…》
That isn't my problem.
何やってる ムッタ｡
早く上に上がれ｡
What are you doing, Mutta?
Climb up here!
発射管制棟にしては小さいな｡
This is small for a blockhouse.
無人の小型ロケットを
飛ばしてた頃のだ｡
It was used when we were launching smaller unmanned rockets.
アポロより前の時代にな｡
We're talking before the Apollo program.
そんな古いの!?
It's that old?
《だ 大丈夫!?このハシゴ…》
I-Is this ladder safe to use?
うわぁ…！
ワシは ここで見るのが
好きなんだ｡静かでいい｡
I love watching launches here.
It's nice and quiet.
ヤングじいさん…｡
Mr. Young...
Huh?
ちょっと いいじゃね～か ここ｡
This place is amazing.
That's what I was telling you.
だから｢いいとこ｣っつっただろ｡
(ﾚﾎﾟｰﾀｰ)マルスワン 打ち上げ
１０分前となりました｡➡
Ten minutes until Mars I will launch.
For a while, there was talk of postponing the launch...
一時は悪天候による中止も
心配されましたが…｡
あと１０分｡
Ten minutes to go.
打ち上げ前から こんなに
にぎやかとは思わなかったぜ｡
I didn't think it would be this lively before the launch.
やっぱりツルミー 晴れ男だねぇ｡
Sunny Tsurumi comes through again.
(鶴見)お役に立てて何よりです｡
I'm glad I could help.
Badump, badump, badump, badump.
Oh, badump, badump, badump...
口で言うな｡
Don't say it out loud.
《私も早く あれに乗りたい！》
I hope I can be up there soon!
珍しくヒビトの
心拍数が高いな～｡➡
For once, Hibito's heart rate is actually high...
さすがに緊張か？
Getting nervous?
No way.
まさかぁ｡
ワクワクが頂点なもんで｡
I'm just super excited.
あと数秒で カウントダウンが
予定されている➡
In a few seconds, we will enter the final built-in hold before the final countdown.
最後のビルト･イン･ホールドに
入ります｡➡
２…１… ９分前｡
カウントダウンをホールド｡➡
2.
1.
T minus 9 minutes.
Hold the countdown.
４５分間の
最後のホールドに入りました｡
Final 45-minute hold has begun.
最後の
ビルト･イン･ホールドに入る｡➡
We've begun the final built-in hold.
燃料！
≪ゴー！≫
Fuel.
Go!
≪ブースター≫
ゴーです！
Boosters.
They're a go.
Sound.
Go.
軌道｡
≪ゴー フライト！≫
Orbit.
Go flight.
≪ネットワーク≫
≪ゴー！≫
Network.
Go.
≪天候≫
Weather.
Go.
よ～し 決行だ｡➡
Okay, we're good to go.
最終カウントダウン開始！
Begin final countdown.
We now begin the final countdown.
これより 最終カウントダウンを
開始します｡
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)かつては ここにも
大勢の人が働いていた｡➡
A lot of people used to work here...
ワシの親父も ワシもな｡➡
Including my dad and me.
親子２代でロケットバカだ｡➡
Two generations of rocket fanatics.
ウハハハ！文句あるか？➡
Got a problem with that?
ロケットやシャトルの打ち上げに
何十年も携わってきた｡➡
I worked on rocket and shuttle launches for decades.
今は引退して ここと同じ
過去のモノになっちまったけどな｡
But now, I've retired and become a relic of the past.
ひっそりと打ち上げを
見守るってのも いい気分だぜ｡
But it feels good to watch the launches from a distance.
キャンディ なめるか？
Want some candy?
届かね～よ｡
I can't reach it.
コントロールいいぞ ワシは｡
いいって｡
I have good control.
It's okay.
《あの中には 日々人が
空を向いて座ってるんだな…》
Hibito's sitting in there, looking up into the sky.
⦅ムッちゃん
俺 今なんとなく…➡
Mu.
You know, I have a feeling...
なんとなく
将来は宇宙飛行士になってさ➡
I just have this feeling that I'll become an astronaut
月に行くような気がしたよ⦆
and go to the moon.
《あれから２０年も…➡
It's been twenty years...
日々人は ずっと空を見て
宇宙だけを目指してきた》
Hibito's spent the entire time looking up at the sky, aiming to go to space.
《そして 今 ちゃんと
そこに座ってんだから➡
And now,
there he is.
ほんと すげぇ奴だな お前は》
He's really something...
よし いいね｡
Looking good.
晴れてきた！
The sun's finally out!
いいとこだな ここは｡
This is a nice place.
I can watch the launch without distractions.
何も気にせず見れる｡
That wall inside of me
《俺の中にいたジャマ者は
ここにはいない》
is gone.
(ｽﾋﾟｰｶｰ:ｱﾅｳﾝｽ)打ち上げ２分前｡➡
T minus 2 minutes.
動力を内部電源に切り替え➡
Orbiter transfers from ground to internal power.
現在 マルスワンは
内部電源で動いています｡➡
Mars I is now on internal power.
フライトデータレコーダー作動｡➡
Start mission recorders.
地上コンピューターから
マルスワンの➡
Transfer control to Mars I flight computer.
フライトコンピューターに
引き継ぎ｡
１分前｡水消音ｼｽﾃﾑ 電源オン｡➡
T minus 1 minute.
Initiate sound suppression water.
Deactivate solid rocket booster joint heaters.
固体ロケット結合ヒーター解除｡
お父さん どうしよう…
飛ぶよ 飛ぶよ！
Oh, no...
It's really going to take off!
ああ 飛ばなきゃ困る｡
Yeah, it's supposed to.
エーピーユー
(ｽﾋﾟｰｶｰ:ｱﾅｳﾝｽ)ＡＰＵ起動！
Start auxiliary power units.
(ﾚﾎﾟｰﾀｰ)え～いよいよ 待ちに待った
打ち上げの瞬間です｡
Everyone, it's the moment we've been waiting for!
３０秒前｡固体ロケットモーターの
ジンバルテスト中｡
T minus 30 seconds.
Booster gimbal profile.
(ｽﾋﾟｰｶｰ:ｱﾅｳﾝｽ)２０秒前｡➡
T minus 20 seconds.
Activate main engine hydrogen burn-off system.
点火システム オン｡➡
Activate sound suppression water.
水消音システム 作動｡➡
１０秒前｡➡
T minus 10 seconds.
ナイン
エイト
９！ ８！➡
9.
8.
7.
セブン
シックス
７！ ６！➡
6.
ファイブ
フォー
５！ ４！➡
5.
4.
スリー
３！➡
3.
２！➡
2.
ワン
１！➡
1.
リフトオフ‼
Liftoff.
Look.
見ろ リフトオフだ｡
We have liftoff.
My right hand spent its days afraid of losing something
but wished to be held by my left hand
I lead you by the hand
Is my hand only there to hold my own hand now?
I can't lose it
Amidst my nagging disappointment that I can do nothing
I felt I wanted to do something
I let go again
I'm not alone in this world
If my hands can only hold two things
then I hope one of them is you
Not alone, not alone
I want our hearts to be connected
I want to be connected
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#31 Rocket Road
＜あれから２０年も
日々人は ずっと空を見て➡
It's been twenty years...
Hibito's spent the entire time looking up at the sky, aiming to go to space.
宇宙だけを目指してきた＞
＜そして 今 ちゃんと
そこに座ってんだから➡
And now, there he is.
ほんと すげぇ奴だな お前は＞
He's really something...
＜見ろ ムッタ｡リフトオフだ＞
Look, Mutta.
We have liftoff.
I finally made it...
＜とうとう来たんだな＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Rocket Road"
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)＜打ち上げは
まだ終わってねえぞ＞
The launch isn't over yet.
＜あのロケットロードが
流れるまでの余韻➡
The launch isn't over until there's no remaining trace of the rocket road.
それを含めて
｢打ち上げ｣っていうんだ＞
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
Dubbing from outer space.
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
スッゲー！
Awesome!